A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Office of Reports, Office Files of Nancy Boggs FA1533
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Office of Reports, Office Files of Nancy Boggs
1967-1986
Rockefeller Archive Center
Boggs, Nancy
Ford Foundation
FA1533
3.83 Cubic Feet 9 Hollinger boxes and 1 3x5 card file box
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas. During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2019 and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2019:064.
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the staff subject files of Nancy Boggs who worked as an Administrative Officer and Graphics Manager in the Ford Foundation's Office of Reports. Files contain correspondence, memos, drafts, scripts, notes, invoices, expense reports, inventories, contracts and agreements, schedules, newspaper clippings, and photographs that document Boggs work on the Foundation's sponsored films and other media projects. The records regard the promotion and distribution of the films as well as the production and planning of those movies. The films that the documents regard concerned subjects like primary healthcare, education, and jobs.
Arrangement
Collection is comprised of one series.
Original order was maintained as much possible.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Subject files, 1967-1986
Biographical / Historical
Nancy Boggs (1930-1994) worked as an Administrative Officer and Graphics Manager in the Ford Foundation's Office of Reports. She played a critical role in the advancement of the Foundation's use of film and television media to promote its activities.
Related Materials
A significant amount of content within the collection regards the Ford Foundation sponsored film "That Our Children Will Not Die". The film is available in FA750 Ford Foundation records, Audiovisual materials
Ford Foundation; Education; Public health -- Nigeria; Primary health care -- Developing countries
- Subject files, 1967-1986; 1; 3.83 Cubic Feet 6 LTR size Hollinger boxes, 3 LGL size Hollinger boxes, and 1 3x5 card file box
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains the subject files that Nancy Boggs created during her time as an Administrative Officer and Graphics Manager in the Ford Foundation's Office of Reports. The bulk of the records regard Boggs' work supporting the planning, production, promotion, and distribution of the Foundation's various sponsored films. Boggs' work on the Institute of Child Health (ICH) film "That Our Children Will Not Die" is particularly well documented in the series, but there are also records concerning films like "Changing Work", "They Call It Wildcat", and "Tomorrow We'll See What Happens" among others. These films chiefly regard topics like primary health care, education, and jobs and job programs. Correspondence, memos, notes, Recommended Grant Actions records (RGAs), contracts and agreements, invoices, and expense reports document how Boggs worked with consultant producers, directors, and film crews and co-sponsor institutions like the ICH in the planning and production of the different films. Similar materials as well as newspaper clippings, drafts, photographs, and inventories document how Boggs assisted the promotion and dissemination of the films.
  The remaining files in the series regard the Office of Reports' promotion of other Ford Foundation activities and the use of television and film media in that kind of promotion.
  - That Our Children Will Not Die film - Transcript and translations, 1978-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - That Our Children Will Not Die film - Promotion, 1978-1986 (Box 1, Folder 4-7)
    - That Our Children Will Not Die - Reel 1, circa 1978; 1/4 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9997)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
      First part of Ford Foundation sponsored film "That Our Children Will Not Die" about the Institute of Child Health (ICH) in Nigeria.
    - That Our Children Will Not Die - Reel 2, circa 1978; 1/4 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9998)
      Second part of Ford Foundation sponsored film "That Our Children Will Not Die" about the Institute of Child Health (ICH) in Nigeria.
  - That Our Children Will Not Die film - Distribution, 1978-1983 (Box 2, Folder 8-10)
  - That Our Children Will Not Die film - Distribution, 1978-1982 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - That Our Children Will Not Die film - Screening, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Institute of Child Health (ICH), University of Lagos, Nigeria - Grant 07790835, That Our Children Will Not Die film, 1970-1978 (Box 3, Folder 14-17)
  - Institute of Child Health (ICH), University of Lagos, Nigeria - Grant 07790835, That Our Children Will Not Die film, 1977-1983 (Box 3, Folder 18-20)
  - Institute of Child Health (ICH), University of Lagos, Nigeria - Grant 07790835, That Our Children Will Not Die film, 1975-1978 (Box 4, Folder 21-22)
  - The Hidden Holyoke photograph exhibit - William Ravanesi, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Ford Foundation films - Awards and reviews, 1975-1983 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Ford Foundation films - Inventories, 1975-1984 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Ford Foundation films - Distribution, 1979-1982 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Ford Foundation films - Copyrights, 1972-1981 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Ford Foundation films - Stills and negatives, circa 1975-1978; File is mainly comprised of still images. These images include film stills and a film negative. (Box 4, Folder 28)
    The film negative and several of the stills in the file are from the Ford Foundation sponsored film "Changing Work". These images are interspersed with a group of stills from the "Household Technicians" episode of the "Are You Listening" series along with correspondence from Martha Stuart Communications to Nancy Boggs. It is unclear why these two groups of unrelated images were mixed together. The file also contains a set of stills related to the Institute of Child Health (ICH), University of Lagos film "That Our Children Will Not Die". A document describing these photographs is included. Photograph 6 in the set appears to be missing from the file.
  - Status and Roles of Women as Factors in Fertility Behavior: A Policy Analysis - Adrienne Germain, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Ford Foundation Assistance in Francophone West Africa, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Redirections in Educational Development - F. Champion Ward, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Original/Asian art, undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Ford Foundation description, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Miscellaneous - National Journal report, Rural Farm Workers: West/Southwest photograph exhibit, etc., 1971-1976 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Public interest law, undated (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Regional Planning Association (RPA) Choices for 1976, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 36-37)
  - Leadership Development Program (LDP) TV release, 1972-1974 (Box 5, Folder 38-39)
  - Ford Foundation films - Contracts, 1967-1975 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Ford Foundation films - Promotion, 1973-1979 (Box 6, Folder 41-42)
  - Film about the Ford Foundation, 1970-1973 (Box 6, Folder 43-44)
  - Job 23-7. Audiovisual Delegated Authority Project (DAP) 739-0011, 1972-1982 (Box 6, Folder 45-46)
  - Arthur Germaise/Donald Brittain - Film about the Ford Foundation, 1970-1971 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Ford Foundation films - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Seattle school desegregation film, 1977-1980 (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - Native American Rights Fund (NARF) - Indian Rights, Indian Law film, 1975-1981 (Box 7, Folder 50-51)
  - Sandell-Film AB and David Hancock - Changing Work film, 1970-1976 (Box 7, Folder 52-54)
  - Music Lessons film - Council on International Nontheatrical Events (CINE), 1982 (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - Music Lessons film - Awards, 1981-1982 (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - Music Lessons film - Promotion and booklet, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Ford Foundation films - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1978-1982 (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - Job 82-18. Sandra Nichols - The Fragile Mountain film, 1981-1983 (Box 8, Folder 59)
  - They Call It Wildcat film - Showing, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 60)
  - They Call It Wildcat film showing invitee index cards, circa 1974 (Box 10)
  - Tutorial Community Project (TCP) - Tomorrow We'll See What Happens film guide, background, and promotion, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 61-62)
  - Tutorial Community Project (TCP) - Delegated Authority Project (DAP) 739-0195, Tomorrow We'll See What Happens film, 1972-1975; File includes one still image. (Box 9, Folder 63-66)
    The still image in the file is a photograph depicting two students. The photograph is mostly likely related to the "Tomorrow We'll See What Happens" film about the Tutorial Community Project (TCP).
  - Changing Work film, 1973-1980; File includes a set of still images. (Box 9, Folder 67-68)
    Photograph negatives in the file are stills from the Ford Foundation sponsored film "Changing Work". Those images would be used in the Foundation's report "A Work Experiment: Six Americans in a Swedish Plant" about the Detroit-Sweden worker exchange program the film concerns.